DR. Khalid Basalama profile 2017

Country/Regional/Group HR& Administration Managing Director.

Saudi National.

Native Arabic & Fluent English.

Born in 1967, Married, 4 children.

basalamak@yahoo.com

Mobile: 00966 50 631 2278

Skype: Dr.Basalama

Medina, KSA.

Summary:

Dr. Khalid Basalama is Country HR& Admin. Director for Viaarabia Group. Used to be General manager for Holiday Villa hotel 5* in KSA, Medinah, Earlier run his own firm investing in realestate operations. Before that Led responsibilities of Human resources department as a Group director for all (4) Rosewood's Hotels in Riyadh "Al Faysalia & Al Khuzama" within 2012. Earlier was Human resources Director for Sunset beach (Resort& Spa) during 2011. Earlier he rejoined Medinah Intercontinental both Hotels in 2008 as joint Human Resources Manager. He had been with Intercontinental as Training Manager from 2003 to 2004. Between those 2 times of working with IHG: He was working with international teams in Mega National Project of E-Government, which was assessing & recommending HR solutions for 60 Government Agencies. He was the senior HR Consultant, he has been the team Leader of Strategic Study in Human Resources Track. After this, he was involved in Organizational Transformation Program, which was another governmental Project worth over \$100 million in which he led the re-engineering of HR Track including training Gov. Human capital. He possesses a Ph.D. in Business Administration enjoying leadership competencies.

http://www.hoteliermiddleeast.com/5909-awardscountdown-hr-person-of-the-year/9/ http://www.hoteliermiddleeast.com/9656-hotelier-awards-shortlist-hrperson-of-the-year/

Experience:

Group HR& Administration Director for KSA and Dubai @ Viaarabia

Aug. 2015 - Aug. 2016

Job Role: Leading all Human resources department's functions and activities as for all branches in KSA & Dubai, set up a strategy to survive during the KSA'a economic crises in 2016 and lead implementing it successfully.

Group HR Director @ Rosewood Hotels & Resorts

April 2012 - July 2012 (4 months) Left for family reasons but with great start.

Job Role: Leading all Human resources department's functions and activities for all (4) Rosewood's Hotels in Riyadh "2 Al Faysalia & 2 Al Khuzama".

Human Resources Manager @ InterContinental Hotels Group (IHG)

March 2008 - March 2011 (3 years)

Job Role: Leading 2 HR teams for both Medinah Intercontinental Hotels to operate all HR's functions successfully aiming to create colleagues loyalty through high satisfaction's action plans which led to be rewarded by Meddle East& Africa Hotelier award as a 2010 Human Resources Person (1st 5 out of hundreds), please check both links:

http://www.hoteliermiddleeast.com/5909-awards-countdown-hr-person-of-the-year/9/

http://www.hoteliermiddleeast.com/9656-hotelier-awards-shortlist-hr-person-of-the-year/

Senior Human Resources Consultant @ Integrated Vision Group (IVG)

March 2004 - September 2007 (3 years 7 months)

Job Role: Human Resources' consultancy studies, working with international teams in Mega National Project of E-Government which was assessing & recommending solutions for 60 Government Agencies. As the senior HR Consultant, he has been the team Leader of Strategic Study in Human Resources Track. After that he was involved in Organizational Transformation Program which was another governmental Project worth over \$100 million in which he led the re-engineering of HR Track including training Government's Human capital.

Training Manager @ InterContinental Hotels Group (IHG)

January 2003 - June 2004 (1 year 6 months)

Job Role: Human Resources / Training: Train and Leading training teams for the 3 Intercontinental hotels in Madinah that period to assure brand standard implementations for both "off job" and "on job" training programs and SOPs.

Zone Superintendent at SAUDI BIN LADEN GROUP (Operation& Maintenance)

June 1998 - April 2003 (4 years 11 months)

Company Industry: Operating & Maintenance

Job Role: Management: Leading a team of 400 colleagues in Medina Haram's project by specific quality standards and succeed to be ISO certified.

Education:

Washington International University:

Doctorate Ph.D., Business Administration (DL),

2001 - 2003

King Abdul-Aziz university:

Bachelor degree from college of Human sciences.

Graduate in 1993

Some says & clues describing Dr. Khalid Basalam's career:

http://www.hoteliermiddleeast.com/5909-awards-countdown-hr-person-of-the-year/9/

http://www.hoteliermiddleeast.com/9656-hotelier-awards-shortlist-hr-person-of-the-year/

- His strategic way is encouraging the contributions of others; he listens and builds on suggestions, to create the ownership of next steps among colleagues and helps others gett a strong sense of job satisfaction from contributing.
- He achieved within the Middle East and Africa region the Hotelier award competition up to short list in HR person for 2010.
- Dr. Khalid practicing updated ways in daily work life as he is a PhD Holder in Business Administration from of Washington international University.
- Khalid is responsible for a staff satisfaction figure of 89.3%, a ranking of fourth out of 64 hotels in the MENA region.
- He has implemented an E-Government solution for colleagues' personal needs from external agencies as well as establishing an E-Library (including all IHG available products) in the hotel server.
- Khalid has also ensured colleagues' satisfaction was enhanced by incorporating 24/7 wireless internet facilities, recreation and gym facilities in the staff housing.

- With a door that is always open to staff, employees are encouraged to speak out and share their difficulties, distress, feelings, views, advices and ideas
- As well as looking after the recreational side of hotel life, frequently
 arranging inter-departmental and inter-hotels sport competition as well as
 indoor games, Khalid has created cultural awareness between the 20
 nationalities working together in the hotel.
- He is an ideal HR personality with genuine leadership skills. He is an asset of Intercontinental Hotels K.S.A. and IHG as well.
- He is responsible for HR depts. for 2 intercontinental hotels in Madinah, Saudi Arabia.
- He has rejoined Madinah InterContinental Hotels in 2008 as a joint Human Resources Manager as previously he was working with capacity of Training and Development Manager.
- Since joining, he is untiringly working along with his team to establish a modern HR team to make Madinah IC hotels a great place to work for everyone and let our people love our jobs by keeps encouraging living IHG's values.
- Previously he was working with international teams in Mega National Project of E-Government which was assessing & recommending new solutions for 60 Govt.
 Agencies as the senior HR Consultant. There he was the team Leader of Strategic Study in Human Resources Track.
- After that he was involved in Organizational Transformation Program which was another Mega governmental Project worth over \$100 million in which he led the reengineering of HR Track including training Gov. Human capital. Builds a network across different levels of the organization and stays in productive contact with people, tapping into expertise elsewhere in the organization to be more effective.
- His strategic way is encouraging the contributions of others; listens and builds on suggestions, to create the ownership of next steps among colleagues& help others getting a strong sense of job satisfaction from contributing.
- He is amazing in creating leaders by assigning one colleague every time in many occasions to be a project manager and showing him trust, giving suitable training, encouraging & delegating all needed authorities to him with keep unifying strategic objectives& leadership competencies with continuance observing& developing.
 Infact; most of team members who were working with him "somehow" became leaders.
- He supports and lead assigned project manager by him strategically in a very high level to boost colleague's moral & self confidence, and let colleagues appear in scene & refer all successful's recognitions to the project manager& his team not to himself. He is also encouraging all other leaders to practice same methodology in all levels in the organization.
- He is a great Personality Analyst who can analyze employees' personality and tell them where they could give their 100% efforts which been recognized by IHG's leaders by inviting him to be assessor in "IHG's Future Leaders Program" in KSA.

Below is some achievement of Dr. Khalid amongst his team:

Employee satisfaction survey -2010 shows the degree of staff satisfaction in Dar Al Iman Intercontinental Hotel where 99% of staff has been participated in this

- engagement survey conducted by TNS. The overall score is achieved 90.3% and our ranking is 12 out of 66 hotels in Middle East and Africa region.
- Another hotel Dar Al Hijra Intercontinental hotel scored 81.4% with 99% response rate as well and ranked 19 out off 66 hotels in MEA region
- > Implementation of E-Government solution for colleagues' personal needs from governmental agencies.
- Recommend& follow up to establish E-Library (including all IHG available products) in the hotel server to access to all as a share folder.
- > Support other leaders & supervisors by IHG leadership competences for better levels.

Ensure colleague's satisfactions and compatibilities in daily life needs i.e.

- ➤ Well maintained staff housing with 24/7 free wireless internet facilities, recreation and gym facilities in same premises.
- Open door meetings 2 times yearly with each departmental staff separately to speak out and share their difficulties, distress, feelings, views, advices and ideas etc. without the present of departmental superiors
- Frequently arranged inter-departmental and inter-hotels sport competition as well as indoor games. In 2010 there was an inter-departmental indoor game, one Football tournament.
- Guiding and leading to a cricket tournament which was successfully organized through hotels' team for is the first time in the city. A total 12 other premium from deferent Cos. has participated in this tournament.
- > Support creating cultural awareness between 20 nationalities working together in both IC Madinah hotels.
- Celebrate regularly individual staff delightful occasion i.e. Birthdays, new baby born new marriage as well as every single achievement of staff.
- ➤ Celebrating national days separately for each group of nationality working in the hotel.
- > Recognitions and rewards program throughout the year.
- Organized frequent staff outing by colleagues' desires.
- Ensure colleagues' satisfaction by implementation of daily staff restaurant inspection by active volunteered colleagues as a rotation schedule.
- Establish new Training and development section to assist facilitating and delivering all IHG training and development opportunities for everyone to grow as IHG promised to extend the Room to grow.
- Ensuring communicating training activities by multi languages to assure no language barrier.
- ➤ Continuous struggle to encourage staff to follow IHG's values "winning ways" (Do the right thing, Show we care, Aim higher, celebrate difference and work better together) and deliver the Room to be yourself (Room to have a great start, Room to be involve, Room to grow and room for you)
- ➤ Keep close informal communications with colleagues to identify colleagues' needs and fulfill their requirements in order to ensure the positive work environment.

- ➤ Emphasizing on individual treatment method in all level to overcome the challenges by assuring 1 to 1 meeting between each colleague with his line direct manager.
- > Directing to set real personal development plan for each and every colleague in the hotel.
- Chosen as an assessor for IHG's Future Leadership Program. Top Graduates of universities and college from all over the Saudi Arabia are applied for this program. Also he was presenter of this program in many universities and colleges within KSA.
- Assuring readiness of succession plan by implementing rotation program among HR's team with Personal development plan & communicating all standard information within team & Hotels to keep self & others updated. And operations analysis to anticipate the needs especially due to high turnover expectations in the organization.
- ➤ Plan ahead by Preparing future's team by dealing with Hotel and Tourism College in Madinah to provide practical trainings and assessing for their students in last semester then to attract high potentials to employ in both properties which is rewarded by College authority.
- > By his team work Rewarded by Madinah Govt. Authority for reaching highest level of Nationalization which is 35 %.

Thank you for your valuable time to read my CV, Khalid